The oceans cover two-thirds of our planet.
تغطى المحيطات ثلثى كوكبنا.
They provide half the oxygen we breathe.
فهى تمدنا بنصف الاكسجين الذى نتنفسه.
They moderate our climate.
وتعًدل مناخنا
And they provide jobs and medicine and food
وتوفر فرص العمل والدواء والغذاء
including 20 percent of protein to feed the entire world population.
تشمل 20% من البروتين لتغذية سكان العالم بأسره.
People used to think that the oceans were so vast
طالما اعتقد الناس بأنها كانت شاسعه جدا
that they wouldn't be affected by human activities.
وانها لن تتأثر بالانشطة البشرية.
Well today I'm going to tell you about a serious reality
حسناً اليوم سأخبركم بواقع خطير
that is changing our oceans called ocean acidification,
وهو تغيًر محيطاتنا ويسمى ذلك بتحمض المحيطات،
or the evil twin of climate change.
أو توأم الشر لتغيير المناخ.
Did you know that the oceans have absorbed 25 percent of all of the carbon dioxide
هل كنت تعلم ان المحيطات تمتص 25 بالمائة من اجمالى ثانى اكسيد الكربون
that we have emitted to the atmosphere?
المنبعث الى الغلاف الجوى؟
Now this is just another great service provided by the oceans
والآن هذه مجرد خدمة عظيمة اخرى تمنحها المحيطات
since carbon dioxide is one of the greenhouse gases
بما ان ثانى اكسيد الكربون واحداً من غازات الاحتباس الحرارى
that's causing climate change.
والتى بدورها تسبب فى تغيًر المناخ.
But as we keep pumping more and more and more
ولكن بما إننا نضخ بالمزيد والمزيد والمزيد
carbon dioxide into the atmosphere
من ثانى اكيد الكربون فى الغلاف الجوى
more is dissolving into the oceans.
فإن المزيد يذوب فى المحيطات
And this is what's changing our ocean chemistry.
وهذا ما يغير من كيمياء محيطاتنا
When carbon dioxide dissolves in seawater,
عندما يذوب ثانى اكسيد الكربون فى مياه البحر،
it undergoes a number of chemical reactions.
يمر بعدد من التفاعلات الكيميائية.
Now lucky for you,
الأن ولحسن حظكم،
I don't have time to get into the details of the chemistry for today.
ليس لدي الوقت اليوم للحديث فى تفاصيل هذه الكيمياء .
But I'll tell you as more carbon dioxide enters the ocean,
ولكننى سأخبركم اكثر من ذلك بدخول ثانى اكسيد الكربون المحيط،
the seawater pH goes down.
ينخفض الأس الهيدروجينى لمياه البحر.
And this basically means that there is an increase in ocean acidity.
واساساً هذا يعني ان هناك زيادة فى حموضة المحيط.
And this whole process is called ocean acidification.
وهذه العملية برمتها تسمى تحمض المحيطات .
And it's happening alongside climate change.
وهذا يحدث بجانب تغير المناخ.
Scientists have been monitoring ocean acidification for over two decades.
استمر العلماء بمراقبة ظاهرة تحمض المحيطات لاكثر من عقدين .
This figure is an important time series in Hawaii,
هذا الرسم البيانى هو تسلسل زمنى مهم فى هاواى.
and the top line shows steadily increasing concentrations of carbon dioxide,
يظهر الخط العلوى الزيادة المطرده فى تركيزات ثانى اكسيد الكربون ،
or CO2 gas, in the atmosphere.
او غاز ثانى اكسيد الكربون فى الغلاف الجوى .
And this is directly as a result of human activities.
وهذه هى النتيجة المباشرة للأنشطة البشرية .
The line underneath shows the increasing concentrations of carbon dioxide
يظهر الخط الذى يلية زيادة تركيزات ثانى اكسيد الكربون
that is dissolved in the surface of the ocean
المذاب فى سطح المحيط.
which you can see is increasing at the same rate
التى يمنكم ان ترونها فى تزايد بنفس معدل
as carbon dioxide in the atmosphere since measurements began.
ثانى اكسيد الكربون منذ ان بدأت عمليات القياس.
The line on the bottom shows then shows the change in chemistry.
السطر الذى بالأسفل يبين التغيير فى الكيماء.
As more carbon dioxide has entered the ocean,
بسبب دخول الكثير من ثانى اكيد الكربون الى المحيط،
the seawater pH has gone down,
انخفض الأس الهيدروجينى لمياه البحر،
which basically means there has been an increase in ocean acidity.
وهذا اساساً يعنى ان هناك زيادة فى حموضة المحيط.
Now in Ireland, scientists are also monitoring ocean acidification --
الأن فى ايرلندا ، يراقب العلماء ايضاً تحمض المحيطات --
scientists at the Marine Institute and NUI Galway.
العلماء بمعهد البحرية والجامعة الدولية فى ايرلندا جالواى.
And we, too, are seeing acidification at the same rate
و نحن، ايضا، نرى التحمض بنفس معدل
as these main ocean time-series sites around the world.
هذه السلاسل الزمنية للمحيطات الرئيسية بمواقع حول العالم
So it's happening right at our doorstep.
هذا ما يحدث على عتبة بابنا.
Now I'd like to give you an example of just how we collect our data
والأن اريد ان أعطى لكم مجرد مثال على كيف نجمع بيناتنا
to monitor a changing ocean.
لرصد المحيط المتغير.
Firstly we collect a lot of our samples in the middle of winter.
أولاً نجمع كثير من عيناتنا فى أواسط الشتاء.
So as you can imagine, in the North Atlantic
حتى يمكنك أن تتخيل، فى شمال الأطلسى
we get hit with some seriously stormy conditions --
عصفت بنا احوال جوية قاسية - -
so not for any of you who get a little motion sickness,
ليس بالقليل منكم من يصابون بدوار البحر،
but we are collecting some very valuable data.
ولكن نحن نجمع بعض البيانات القيمة.
So we lower this instrument over the side of the ship,
لذلك ننزل بهذه الأله على جانب السفينه،
and there are sensors that are mounted on the bottom
وهناك أجهزة استشعار يتم تركيبها فى القاع.
that can tell us information about the surrounding water,
والتى يمكن ان تعطينا معلومات عن المياه المحيطة بها،
such as temperature or dissolved oxygen.
مثل درجة الحرارة او نسبة الاكسجين المذاب.
And then we can collect our seawater samples in these large bottles.
وبعدها نستطيع ان نجمع عيناتنا من المياه فى هذه الزجاجات الضخمه.
So we start at the bottom, which can be over four kilometers deep
هكذا نبدأ من القاع، والذى يمكن ان يزيد عمقه عن 4 كيلو متر
just off our continental shelf,
قبالة الجرف القارى لدينا،
and we take samples at regular intervals right up to the surface.
وناخذ عينات على فترات دورية وصولا لسطح المياه
We take the seawater back on the deck,
نأخذ المياه مره اخرى على ظهر السفينه،
and then we can either analyze them on the ship
وبعد ذلك يمكننا ان نحلله على السفينه
or back in the laboratory for the different chemicals parameters.
أو فى المختبر حيث المواد الكيميائة المختلفة.
But why should we care?
لكن لماذا يجب أن نهتم؟
How is ocean acidification going to affect all of us?
كيف لتحمض المحيط ان يؤثر علينا؟
Well, here are the worrying facts.
حسناً، هنا الحقائق المؤسفه.
There has already been an increase in ocean acidity of 26 percent
هناك بالفعل زيادة فى حمضية المحيطات بنسبة 26 %
since pre-industrial times, which is directly due to human activities.
منذ عصور ما قبل الصناعه، والذي يعود مباشراً إلى الأنشطة البشرية.
Unless we can start slowing down our carbon dioxide emissions,
إذا لم نبدأ بتقليل انبعثاتنا من ثانى اكسيد الكربون،
we're expecting an increase in ocean acidity of 170 percent
فنحن نتوقع زيادة فى حموضة المحيط إلى 170 %
by the end of this century.
بحلول نهاية هذا القرن.
I mean this is within our children's lifetime.
وذلك خلال حياة اطفالنا وهذا ما اعنيه
This rate of acidification is 10 times faster
معدل التحمض ذلك اسرع 10 مرات
than any acidification in our oceans for over 55 million years.
من اى تحمض اخر فى محيطاتنا على مدار 55 مليون عام.
So our marine life have never, ever experienced
لذلك حياتنا البحرية لم ولن تشهد
such a fast rate of change before.
مثل هذا المعدل السريع من قبل.
So we literally could not know how they're going to cope.
كذلك نحن حرفيا لانعلم كيف سيتكيفون مع هذا.
Now there was a natural acidification event millions of years ago,
الأن كان هناك حادثة تحمض طبيعى منذ ملايين السنين،
which was much slower than what we're seeing today.
كان أبطأ بكثير مما نراه اليوم.
And this coincided with a mass extinction of many marine species.
وتزامن ذلك مع الانقراض الجماعى لكثير من الفصائل البحريه.
So is that what we're headed for?
فهل هذا ما نتوجه اليه؟
Well, maybe.
حسنا، ربما.
Studies are showing some species are actually doing quite well
تظهر الدراسات ان بعض الفصائل فى الواقع تعمل بصورة جيده
but many are showing a negative response.
لكن العديد منها يظهر نتيجة سلبية.
One of the big concerns is as ocean acidity increases,
ومن اهم المخاوف انه كلما زادت حمضية المحيطات،
the concentration of carbonate ions in seawater decrease.
تنخفض نسبة تركيز ايونات الكربونات فى مياه البحر.
Now these ions are basically the building blocks
والأن هذه الايونات اساساً هى لبنة البناء
for many marine species to make their shells,
للعديد من الفصائل البحرية لبناء قشرتها الخارجيه،
for example crabs or mussels, oysters.
مثل سرطان البحر أو بلح البحر والمحار.
Another example are corals.
مثال آخر الشعب المرجانية.
They also need these carbonate ions in seawater
فهى إيضا تحتاج ايونات الكربونات فى المياه
to make their coral structure in order to build coral reefs.
لصنع بنيتها المرجانية من ثم بناء الشعب المرجانية .
As ocean acidity increases
بسبب ازدياد حمضية المحيط
and the concentration of carbonate ions decrease,
وانخفاض تركيز ايونات الكربونات ،
these species first find it more difficult to make their shells.
تجد هذه الانواع لأول مره ان بناء قشرتها امر بالغ الصعوبة.
And at even even lower levels, they can actually begin to dissolve.
وحتى فى المستويات الادنى يمكن ان تَنحل .
This here is a pteropod, it's called a sea butterfly.
هذه هنا جناجيات الأرجل ، وتسمى فراشة البحر.
And it's an important food source in the ocean for many species,
وهى مصدر غذائى مهم للعديد من الفصائل البحرية ،
from krill to salmon right up to whales.
من الكرل إلى السلمون وصولا إلى الحيتان.
The shell of the pteropod was placed into seawater
وضِعَت قشرة جناحيات الارجل داخل مياه البحر
at a pH that we're expecting by the end of this century.
فى درجة الحموضه التى توقعناها بحلول نهاية القرن.
After only 45 days at this very realistic pH,
بعد 5 أيام فقط فى هذه الحموضه الواقعيه جدا،
you can see the shell has almost completely dissolved.
تستطيعوا أن تروا القشرة وقد أوشكت تماماً على التحلل.
So ocean acidification could affect right up through the food chain --
لذلك فإن تحمض المحيطات يمكنه ان يؤثر مباشرة من خلال السلسة الغذائية --
and right onto our dinner plates.
حتى أطباق عشائنا.
I mean who here likes shellfish? Or salmon?
اقصد هنا مثل القشريات ؟ او السالمون؟
Or many other fish species
أو آى من الانواع العديدة الأخرى
whose food source in the ocean could be affected?
ممن مصادر غذاؤة سوف تتأثر ؟
These are cold-water corals.
هذا هو مرجان المياه البارده.
And did you know we actually have cold-water corals in Irish waters,
هل كنتم تعلمون ان لدينا بالفعل مرجان المياه الباردة فى المياه الأيريلندية ،
just off our continental shelf?
فقط قبالة الجرف القارى لدينا؟
And they support rich biodiversity, including some very important fisheries.
حيث ثراء التنوع البيولوجى، وبعض المصايد السمكية الهامة.
It's projected that by the end of this century,
ومن المتوقع انه بحلول نهاية هذا القرن ،
70 percent of all known cold-water corals in the entire ocean
نسبة70% من جميع شعاب المياه الباردة المعروفة داخل المحيط بأكمله
will be surrounded by seawater that is dissolving their coral structure.
سوف تحاط بمياه البحر التى تُحلل بنيته المرجانية.
The last example I have are these healthy tropical corals.
أخر مثال لدى هو الشعاب المرجانية الأستوائية الصحيه.
They were placed in seawater at a pH we're expecting by the year 2100.
لقد تم وضعهم فى مياه البحر عند حموضه توقعناها بحلول نهاية عام 2100.
After six months, the coral has almost completely dissolved.
بعد 6 أشهر، أوشكت الشعبه على التحلل تماماَ.
Now coral reefs support
الأن الشعاب المرجانية تدعم
25 percent of all marine life in the entire ocean.
25% من الحياة البحرية فى المحيط بأكمله.
All marine life.
جميع الحياة البحرية .
So you can see: ocean acidification is a global threat.
فكما ترون: تحمض المحيط هو تهديد عالمى.
I have an eight-month-old baby boy.
لدى طفل عمره ثمانية أشهر.
Unless we start now to slow this down,
إذا لم نبدأ الأن لتخفيض هذا ،
I dread to think what our oceans will look like when he's a grown man.
أخشي أن افكر ما ستكون عليه محيطاتنا عندما يصبح رجلاً.
We will see acidification.
سوف نرى التحمض.
We have already put too much carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
نحن نطلق الكثير من ثانى اكسيد الكربون بالجو.
But we can slow this down.
لكن يمكننا أن نقلل من ذلك.
We can prevent the worst-case scenario.
يمكن أن نمنع أسوأ سيناريو محتمل.
The only way of doing that
الطريقة الوحيدة لمنعه
is by reducing our carbon dioxide emissions.
هى بتخفيض إنبعاثات ثانى اكسيد الكربون.
This is important for both you and I, for industry, for governments.
وهذا مهم لكم ولى وللصناعات وللحكومات.
We need to work together, slow down global warming
نريد أن نعمل سوياَ، لنبطئ من الأحتباس الحرارى
slow down ocean acidification
نبطئ من عملية تحمض المحيطات
and help to maintain a healthy ocean and a healthy planet
ونساعد فى الحفاظ على محيط صحى وكوكب صحى
for our generation and for generations to come.
لجيلنا وللأجيال القادمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)